<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Boot on Sanketh's Blog</title><link>https://sankethbk.github.io/blog/tags/boot/</link><description>Recent content in Boot on Sanketh's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.155.2</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sankethbk.github.io/blog/tags/boot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Characteristics of MBR Code</title><link>https://sankethbk.github.io/blog/posts/boot/2025-07-07-characteristics-of-mbr-code/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethbk.github.io/blog/posts/boot/2025-07-07-characteristics-of-mbr-code/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="bios-boot-recap"&gt;BIOS Boot Recap&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, we saw that after the BIOS firmware is loaded, it searches for a bootable device from a list of storage options, such as a hard drive, SSD, USB, or network interface. The BIOS identifies a valid bootable device by checking for the &lt;code&gt;0x55AA&lt;/code&gt; signature at the end of the first sector. Once found, it loads the 512 bytes from this sector (LBA 0), which is known as the Master Boot Record (MBR).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>What happens when you turn on computer?</title><link>https://sankethbk.github.io/blog/posts/boot/2025-07-02-how-computer-boots/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sankethbk.github.io/blog/posts/boot/2025-07-02-how-computer-boots/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="1-poweron--hardware-reset"&gt;1. Power‑On &amp;amp; Hardware Reset&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="1-powergood-signal"&gt;1. Power‑Good Signal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power supply stabilizes voltages and asserts a “Power‑Good” (PWR_OK) line to the motherboard. All devices receive power and begin to initialize themselves. The Central Processing Unit (CPU) is initially held in a reset mode, meaning it&amp;rsquo;s not yet executing instructions. The memory layout is powered up, although the RAM itself has no content since it&amp;rsquo;s volatile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="2-cpu-reset-vector"&gt;2. CPU Reset Vector&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reset vector is a predetermined memory address where the CPU begins execution after being powered on or reset. On x86 processors, this address is typically &lt;code&gt;0xFFFFFFF0&lt;/code&gt; (near the top of the 4GB address space). When the CPU comes out of reset, its program counter (instruction pointer) is automatically set to this address. The motherboard&amp;rsquo;s memory mapping ensures that this address points to the BIOS/UEFI firmware ROM chip, so the very first instruction the CPU executes comes from the firmware.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>